welcome to meditating with genre video
I'm a cognitive psychologist and
cognitive scientists at the University
of Toronto where I teach academically
and scientifically study phenomena like
mindfulness and related phenomena like
insight fluency flow mystical experience
transformative experience higher states
of consciousness the cultivation of
wisdom and the aspiration towards
enlightenment I also have been
practicing a pasta meditation I met a
contemplation Tai Chi Chuan Qigong for
close to 20 years welcome good morning
if you're joining us for the first time
you should know that this is a
progressive course Monday's our Dharma
days and on those Mondays I previous on
previous Monday's I have taught
principles and practice says that build
on previous principles and practices so
it's a progressive course you're welcome
to stay but in order to catch up
I see the distant the sea in the
description links to previous lessons
and previous steps Tuesdays through
Fridays we meet together and sit and
there's question and answers at the end
of all of the cities Monday through
Friday if you have questions please
limit them to the sets of practices that
I'm teaching in this course for broader
questions please go to the monthly Q&A
we're having one this Friday at 3 p.m.
est and what you can do is I'm a more
encompassing question there you know
what's you know how does this these
practices fit into a wider framework
what does this have to do with
cultivating wisdom or responding to the
meaning crisis or giving me resiliency
Lee the resiliency in the face of there
so maybe more philosophical questions
about how does this Buddhist read and
write compare to you know a stoicism or
neoplatonism of Christianity what does
all of this tell me more about this the
connection between all this and
cognitive science so those are the kind
of questions you can ask there so we had
our tenth Dharma lesson
this past Monday which means we are done
the introductory course going forward
on every other Monday alternate
alternating Monday's I will teach a more
advanced technique so next Monday which
will be I believe the 18th there will it
will not be a Dharma day I'll be here
we'll sit together Q&A at the end and
then starting the following Monday we'll
do alternating other days the intent
behind that is to give people a chance
to catch up all material even though
even those of you who have been with me
since the beginning there's a lot of
given you and thus we're going to slow
down the pace so you can absorb it more
practice more and also give people who
are just beginning a chance to catch up
with us ok um some overall reminders
please like this video stream to raise
its visibility in the YouTube algorithm
that will help me reach more people
I think the first lessons video is up to
6,000 views so that's very good thank
you so much for your help I'm trying to
think if there's anything else we need
to talk about I don't think so
I think we're ready to go so please set
your phone to do not disturb get
yourself into your posture and we'll say
well then we will begin when I say begin
begin
you
so they begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
integrate what you cultivated in your
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition
perhaps by reciting the five promises to
yourself
ok so I think we can answer some
questions today first ones from Keira
Krueger or Krueger I seem to get
distracted by a lot of planning what I'm
going to say usually to someone I'm
engaged in conversation with on social
media it happens over and over again I'm
not sure how to handle so this is a very
common thing as I just mentioned it's a
good thing not to meditate right after
you've been engaged in the conversation
because you'll tend to play the tapes
over and over again
so this is where first of all you've got
to do a lot of the repetition thinking
coming back thinking coming back just
get good at catching yourself first and
this will take time and it takes
patience thank you label it thinking
coming back so for a while
don't even try the five factors of
implying mindfulness if you it's very
intense like that just again and again
and again and again catching yourself a
lot right there's remember you're
meditating when you're catching yourself
in distraction not just when your mind
is free from distraction ok so just
practice not a lot sensitize yourself if
you get better and better and that's all
you're trying to do you know trying to
make the destructions go away you're
just trying to get better and better at
noticing when you're distracted and
bringing coming back to your breath
noticing label it thinking thinking
thinking or talking or whatever again
and again and again do that for quite a
while when that start when you've got a
sense that you're much more sensitive
you catch yourself sooner you come back
right and try applying the firefighters
of inquiring mindfulness listen to the
like if it's your voice and the voice of
the person how many voices are there try
not to pay attention to what the
conversation is about try to pay
attention to everything is if the
conversation was taking place in a
language you don't understand
all right and notice you can even up
what identity am i assuming when I'm
with this person you can bring it a bit
of Metta right you know what's what's
the tempo why boy what's what's
happening the rest of my mind in my body
when I'm distracted that way I'm talking
to these other people but for first
first have developed a sensitivity to
notice when you distract it when she
feel that that has really started to
take form and you take shape in you then
apply the five factors of acquiring
mindfulness not to it you also might
want to cut down just right you might
want to notice that maybe this is the
practice of integrity maybe when you're
on social media Allah
that's something is creating patterns I
don't know it know you the created
patterns they're dissonant and sunbae so
how are you maybe pay more attention try
to bring the mindfulness into social
media indirection how are you yeah what
did you mind yelling is it is it
constant with this trying to cultivate
and you should have practice if it's not
then you need to perhaps adjust your
interaction maybe both the quantity and
the quality of your interaction with
social media minha vida' Vichy three
nice allusion to Caesar and his conquest
of Gaul the question it seems more
intuitive me to reverse Praja and breath
any differences no as I mentioned
yesterday for about 20% of the people
the reverse is making is makes more
intuitive sense for them and do it that
way by all means yes no question Maya
sometimes everything becomes effortless
and easy but this state very soon
becomes uncomfortably like a knot like
it's not my territory should I challenge
the state or should I avoid it for now
um so that's interesting I wish I could
talk more to you about this so when it's
effortless and easy and it's just
flowing but the state very soon becomes
uncomfortable so there's something
deeply unfamiliar not my territory to
you and unless you're getting a sense of
a past trauma coming up right trying to
stay with that right because that's
actually part of what we're trying to
achieve in deeper pasta right we're
trying to get to a place where we're
with our own mind isn't familiar to us
where we're opening up
to a different way of inhabiting our
minds in their bodies so remember above
all else this is when your brain prefers
familiarity well all us your brain
prefers familiar sadness over unfamiliar
happiness for example is the brain is
primarily an anticipation machine so
again I don't know your therapeutic
situation and so I try not to be
presumptuous I'm assuming that's not the
case for you under that assumption right
you're doing something I think that's
very very important you're getting to a
place where you're opening up two
aspects of the mind that are unfamiliar
to you and that is a place that affords
transformation opening and change
approach it very carefully slowly but
see if you can come into a more stable
relationship with it try to befriend it
as a Pope right because it's it is
protecting what's potentially happening
there is a more encompassing state of
mind and being is being made available
to you harima past the basement - I'll
pass the past experience taught to since
every square inch of the body slowly
doing only the grounding points for the
top of the head flowing down which mean
seems like not enough contact um yeah I
know and you know Kevin's in has a
version of this - you do the complete
body scan like I said doing most of the
torso and centering it on the dot CN
really emphasizes the rootedness and
said earnest and so that's the
connection from touch each one if you
want to do the full-body scan there's
nothing precluded from doing that that
like I said the problem I find with the
full-body scan is it doesn't it doesn't
really connect very well to the
centering and routing it you know it
obviously would integrate fairly well
with flow but it tends to leave behind
the centering and routing giving them a
bit of emphasis
and priority really helps to strengthen
the foundations for mindfulness but like
if you can do maybe maybe combine them
do the full-body scan and then
especially do the the century and the
routing right exercise see let's see if
that works for you mark the throat it's
good to see mark
struggling with embodied flow likely due
to physical illness tips for enhancing
and body flow anything I can research so
depends what you mean by research I've
written some stuff on flow it's
published in this Oxford Handbook of
spontaneous thought I might figure out a
way to get it to you somehow because the
book itself is kind of expensive but
it's really valuable to have for anybody
who is doing this kind of practice like
I said and I'm still looking into this
and I'm going to start bringing it into
some of the more advanced classes you
need to do a moving technique a more and
body moving typically practice like Tai
Chi Chuan that would really really help
with the embodied flow quite a bit I'll
teach you some are going to teach you
some each one practices some Chicana bit
of Tai Chi I'll be doing that too
walking meditation so that you know I'm
going to give you a bunch of embodied
practices chanting which is a very much
an embodied practice to try and help you
to get a much more comprehensive and
embodied sense of flow a flowing form of
mindfulness which is really what it is
and down in Deepa Pastner I'm finding
myself focusing on the stillness at the
end of exhale and focusing and expanding
on that as that's not right yes as I
mentioned some traditions in fact have a
three-stage what I've practiced this
sometimes and I see its value where you
you know you follow the in and then
there's a space follow the openness
space right and so they already get
people to notice that space where
nothing's happening and then if you are
finding that in deeper Pastner and
you're finding that stillness right
that's great
that's pretty like that I am finding
that stillness the silence the
separation from the motion and the voice
of the speaking mind very liberating
very opening up yes yes hi Rhoda hi
Brett when doing Praja doing the meta
parts do we still alternate between the
three versions of the happy suchness
more less or just use one through the
step I would just you know I'm doing the
meta part
do we still alternate between three
versions healthy happy I'm not sure if I
quite understand you but maybe we you
know I'll be talking to you at some
point more directly let's let's talk
about this in person for us I get a
clear understanding and then I want to
come back and make a note of this when I
come back to that question and then re
answer for everybody publicly but I want
to get a little bit better sense of
what's being asked they're not quite
clear because I can talk to you directly
I'd like to do that and help them with
that another question from Kyra I
noticed what I find a place of body
armor it may be very prevalent during
one set and that I don't notice that are
again for even weeks is that normal yes
because the body armor is boats armor is
reactive to salient events in your life
and the particular patterns of you know
of self deception and defense
I'm not accusing you we all are guilty
of this so please understand but it
reflects particular patterns of
self-defense and reactivity and
habituated right bitumen or alteration
of how information is flowing through
our bodies in our mind and that is
really contextually dependent it will
depend on events that are happening in
the day or things that are triggered in
your memory or particularly
confrontations you have so that is very
very normal
good questions here good questions
Aleksei siminoff practicing looking into
the space between the thoughts and how
they merge I started to get images which
I practically never get even in altered
states is it common yes so what can
often happen as the sort of speaking
part yeah fades away I don't want to
choose my bird very carefully there his
imagery can take its place
almost like hypnagogic hypnagogic
imagery that takes place at that time so
that's quite normal and again it's that
it's like you make when you initially
make that space other ways in which your
brain you know communicates with itself
and represents its processing to itself
can come into the fore in that space
just treat it like the the speaking
thoughts right notice the space between
the images etc but if that's very normal
but some people Walsh reports this and
there's some evidence to back this up
that extensive mindfulness practice can
create synesthesia in individuals so
yeah quite normal
so yes most of my distractions are our
problem of scheduling things that I
should be doing during the day and
things which I have to dress in the long
run should I take cognizance and try to
address them in life well first of all
like I said planning and anticipating is
one of the big things one of big engines
of your mind and so trying to partially
at least step back from the way that is
distracting us at dis identifying with
it is good because it opens up a space
for the kind of thinking that actually
is needed in addition to on try to
enhance my words very carefully in
addition to planning which is a
resilient kind of online coping
because whenever you're planning each
stage of your plan as you undertake it
actually require requires your you know
online coping with that situation it is
and your flexibility and your
mindfulness
so that's one thing and so that leads me
to the point yes I mean you I don't
think you should think of meditation is
something that magically is telling you
which of your plans you need to schedule
I think you should do that I think you
should like I say do practice the
mindfulness and learning how to pull
away from that distraction disidentify
with it use really good rational
reflection that's what that's what it's
for within your planning but what you
can do is think about what I just said
is notice when you're planning are you
making are you acknowledging that you
need to bring mindfulness in this you
need to bring in it pull mental planning
you need to bring it and cope it so is
the planning a way of actually sort of
locking yourself away from something you
don't want to see is it away in which
you are opening yourself up to what
needs to be done but are you doing that
mindfully and are you acknowledging and
making space for coping there always
compliments and is needed for successful
planning and implementing your plans
Harun Gusterson
any reason we should not meditate while
falling asleep at night event yes
because you are training your brain it's
called encoding specificity remember I
taught you that your brain doesn't just
store the information it serves the
entire context I'm not not on the
external context of the internal mental
context when it's storing stuff and so
your training your brain to deeply
associate mindfulness practice with
falling asleep which is the opposite of
what we're trying to achieve here it's
the opposite of what we're trying to
achieve here so that's why it's strongly
recommended against in many many
traditions jet-black
sometimes I stiff for around 30 minutes
before becoming mindful it is only then
that I commence medam Praja is this okay
or should I begin before reaching the
restful state so I'm a little bit I am a
little bit concerned that you're
identifying mindfulness with sort of
being there in a restful state like I
said whenever you're catching yourself a
distraction and coming back to the
breath that's mindfulness it's like
for me that is the quintessence of
mindfulness the ability to get that
insight that allows you to come out of
distraction and come out of habitual and
automatic ways of being so I think
that's important but perhaps what you
mean is it takes you quite a while to
have the core four set up and then and
only then you feel that you're ready to
go into Metta or Praja that's fine
initially I've mentioned this before
but what you want to do is you want to
slowly reduce the time on the core for
right slowly very slowly each time and
that's a bit of push remember right
effort you're always pushing yourself
where you're having to learn once you
can do the core for the next thing you
have to learn is how to do them taking
less time less time less time less time
because you want to move more and more
towards be the core for being second
nature to you the way so that you can
carry them into your life so it's
alright if right now it's taking you
thirty minutes
but because again you have your own
particular universe in credit history
that I don't know of right but once you
have learnt how to find the core for
then slowly start to reduce the time all
right that's the next thing you're
learning okay hopefully I will help and
yeah when I see when I tried to eat the
pasta I sense my pulse around my eyes
are in my chest should I meditate on as
a distraction what if that feeling does
not go away
you can meditate on the distraction
you're not trying to make the feeling
going the way you're trying to meditate
on how it attracted your attention right
but what's happening by the way which is
a good thing then is your interoceptive
awareness is increasing your ability to
pick up on your own pulse means that
your insula so ability to pick up on
your own inner bodily states is
increasing and that also by the way is
predictive of your ability to pick up on
other people's mental states so that's a
good thing that's happening I would and
again you're not trying to make the
pulse and go away right you're trying to
get it so that
can be off here in the background
burbling and not taking center stage but
when it is distracting you and becoming
center stage you're not trying to
medicate it away you're just what what
was the state of mind like like the five
factors of mindfulness that brought this
centering of it into my mind that's what
you're actually applying to five hunters
of employing mindfulness to Karima do we
have to couple the papasa and meta with
breath it's a good idea to do so but you
mean do you mean within Prasanna or
I mean because meta on its own is not
coupled to the breath but passed on and
Sonja's but if you mean within Praja
yeah you do because you you you want to
keep that roundedness in the living
movement of your body integrated with
whatever you're doing in your mind you
don't want to get just in your head
that that can be that can be it's a kind
of way in which we get into certain
spiritual bullshitting I'm not accusing
you of this prema
I'm not what I'm saying because I
noticed this in my own life where we
think that to be in our head and sort of
the wonderful spaces in our head is sort
of to be spiritual and so there's a
danger I think if we uncouple our mind
motion from our body motion of getting
you know to having reminded to be any
earthly good matthew McCready when we're
finding our flow and trying to get an
optimal grip between our focus on our
stomach area the rest of our torso are
we trying to make both feelings the same
level of detail or a greater detail on
the stomach area than the peripheral
toast yes exactly exactly once you've
found the field
this becomes focal and it's much more
detailed than this which is vaguer in
the same way that when I'm focusing for
example right now on the camera it's
quite detailed and then this although I
have an awareness of this it is much
less detailed because it's backgrounded
exactly exactly
okay I think this will be last question
for today will take from Alexi siminoff
any thoughts on adding biofeedback
like heart math HG bar sensor to the
practice um that's interesting because
there is some evidence its preliminary
that pairing this practice with
biofeedback can enhance what hasn't been
studied and I have a concern about is
does that transfer to people's lives or
does it lock them into having to use the
machine
I've been something analogous I'm not
recommending it I'm not a medical
professional I was doing it as a
researcher where I have paired
mindfulness practices with transcranial
direct current stimulation and I noticed
that there was a powerful synergy
between those two and it's did seem to
carryover and transferred to my life as
a whole I'm not recommending you doing
that I'm just saying that I'm very
interested scientifically in the
possibility that we may be able to
integrate these cyber technologies with
the psycho technology of mindfulness in
a mutually enhancing way so I'm very
very interested in that I recommend like
that you do a lot more research and you
wait for the science to catch up for a
bit before you sort of ad hoc experiment
on this but you know you you of course
are an adult and if you think if you
come to a rational and reflective
decision that it seems safe and
appropriate and it doesn't seem to be
locking people in then perhaps try it I
recommend if you're going to do it that
you try and do it a little bit more
scientifically keep it journal take
notes
exception so everybody the questions are
getting well they've always been so good
and they're just really really good
that's it's it's so much fun thank you
for joining and I want to thank my dear
friend and techno major Moore for all of
his work behind the scenes and my
beloved son Jason he's always there
helping out please like this video to
raise its visibility on the YouTube
algorithm please subscribe to this
channel to be notified of the next video
and also to find you know all the
lectures and awakening from the meaning
crisis or all the discussions and voices
with or making about this larger context
of trying to integrate science and
spirituality together for the
cultivation of wisdom
invite others please who might benefit
by sharing this series we will be doing
this every weekday morning at 9:30
Eastern Time uh and then as I said next
Monday is not a Dharma day but the
Monday after that because we will do
every other Monday will be Dharma day
every day we'll be sitting Monday
through Friday but only every other
Monday going forward will now be at
normative so please remember continuity
practice much more important than
quantity there is no enemy worse than
your own mind there is no ally no friend
greater than your own life take care
everyone
keep practicing see you tomorrow